<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Expedient or a sure &amp; easy way of reducing all dissenters whatsoever to an exact &amp; sincere obedience both to our ecclesiastical &amp; civil government</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39066</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19639792</idno>
  <idno type="VID">109264</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248552275</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41147</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">19639792</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39066)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109264)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1685:70)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Expedient or a sure &amp; easy way of reducing all dissenters whatsoever to an exact &amp; sincere obedience both to our ecclesiastical &amp; civil government</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Religious tolerance --  Great Britain --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Liberty of conscience --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109264:1"/>
            <head>AN EXPEDIENT OR A sure &amp; easy way of <hi>Reducing</hi> all <hi>Dissenters</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever to an exact &amp; sincere <hi>Obedience</hi> both to our <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> &amp; <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AMong all the great nations that have been, no man I beleive can show me the example of <hi>England,</hi> which being not only still intire under the Rule of its lawful Governour, but also a great deal stronger in it selfe, by the happy conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Scotland</hi> (its former dangerous enemy) should neverthelesse since the <hi>Reformation</hi> bee <hi>de facto</hi> much weaker, &amp; consequently lesse considerable to our <hi>Neighbours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>English men,</hi> of what persuasion or intrest soever, unanimously conclude that our differences in <hi>Religion</hi> are the cause; &amp; therefore as some of every <hi>Opinion</hi> have proposed their <hi>Expedients</hi> for the cure of this misfortune, so I hope I may take the same liberty, &amp; throw in my mite also, being induc'd thereunto by the affection I bear my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which I suppose moved the rest, that have already written: and though I am borne a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whose <hi>Liturgy</hi> &amp; <hi>Rites</hi> are so worthy of admiration, yet I shall do what I can (as far as 'tis lawful) to bridle in my <hi>Zeale,</hi> least seeming too partial, I should rather harden than mollifie our <hi>dissenting Brethren;</hi> who happen (which is the misery of it) to be too numerous &amp; considerable in this poor distracted <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We all know that the whole kingdome as to <hi>Divine Worship</hi> is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (besides its subdivisions) into these four great Parties, <hi>viz: Church of England men, Presbyterians, Independents,</hi> &amp; <hi>Papists;</hi> the three last of which we call <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> as contrary to the present Religion establish'd.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Church of England</hi> is farr more numerous than any, and has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in it of all ranks and conditions; but it seem's not so full of <hi>Zeale</hi> as the others, because it abound's with men that are too much in love with humane Interest, or have no Religion at all; for these ever flock to that <hi>Church</hi> which is in power, whether true or false.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have generally on their side the <hi>Corporations,</hi> &amp; all formal men, which they are pleas'd to call the <hi>sober part of the Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n;</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109264:2"/>but as they are rich, so they lye more open to be harass'd, whensoever the black day of tribulation happen's.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Independents</hi> or <hi>Phanatiques</hi> consist only in <hi>Artizans,</hi> &amp; the meanest of the Land, &amp; yet are in two things very consid rable; as first, let the <hi>Government</hi> do what it will with them, they cannot be much poorer, so that in three months they will recover, &amp; be as they were; In the next place, There <hi>crafts</hi> &amp; <hi>tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> are of great concernment to us.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Papists</hi> there are seven parts of ten, Gentlemen, &amp; people of great quality, &amp; therefore they fancy that their Religion is probaly the truest, because it has been profess'd here all along by so many men of parts &amp; fashion; and boast that it is only through Ignorance, or want of attention that the whole Nation is not as blinde as themselves. As for <hi>Persecution</hi> they are not much terrified at it, having (as they beleive) manfully endur'd it so many years; besides by long practice they know not only all the wayes imaginable to evade the penalties of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> but also by their birth have Relations in all offices, &amp; employments, that alwaies did, &amp; still do helpe them when they are in danger to be whipt by us.</p>
            <p>This then in three words being the <hi>interest</hi> and <hi>state</hi> of each party, wee may the easier finde out a <hi>Remedy</hi> for our <hi>disorders,</hi> which have ruin'd, or at best strangely shatter'd one of the most flourishing <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p>Ever since the <hi>happy Restauration of his Majesty,</hi> there hath been still a great cry in all quarters for <hi>Liberty of conscience,</hi> to which I have been greatly inclin'd, not only out of compassion to well meaning deluded souls, but out of conviction also that it would totally root out all <hi>Sects,</hi> &amp; erronious <hi>Opinions</hi> from among us: &amp; seeing we have sound by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that <hi>severity</hi> has neither destroy'd <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> which is so ridiculous to every body but its Professors: nor yet prevented a troublesome brood of our own, I say considering this, we ought to try what <hi>mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> will effect, since all wise men alter those projects which they finde deficient: at least we may make tryal of it for a while, as our matchlesse <hi>Parliaments</hi> do, that enact often lawes to continue but for so long, to be the better able to see whether they may reape the proposed advantage by them; Nor can this tryal be any wayes prejudicial to us, if it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger neither the souls of men, nor cause a disturbance in the <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis impossible,</hi> (according to the profession of all our most learned <hi>Protestants</hi>) <hi>to hazard our Salvation by Opinions whilst we agree in that main Fundamental,</hi> to wit, <hi>The satisfaction of our Saviour Iesus Christ;</hi> for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109264:2"/>otherwise we must shipwrack our selves, whether we will or no, on the unavoidable rocks of <hi>Popery;</hi> because if there should yet be any thing more, which we are necessarily to beleive, an <hi>infallible Interpreter,</hi> and <hi>Magisterial Iudge</hi> to guide the ignorant &amp; unlearned would consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow; <hi>Magisteriall</hi> I say, because a poor simple man must implicitely believe, as not being ever able to comprehend or understand some truths; &amp; <hi>infallible,</hi> least men might be still doubting whether yet they are in the right or no.</p>
            <p>No marvel then that <hi>Mr. Chillingworth</hi> (the miracle of his age) sticks close to this, thinking it very strange a man should be damn'd for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he cannot comprehend; &amp; therefore layes down <hi>Repentance from dead works, and a beliefe in the comming &amp; merits of Christ,</hi> as the only <hi>Fundamentall</hi> amongst <hi>Christians,</hi> &amp; as a thing adequate to every ordinary capacity. The <hi>Papists</hi> who would fain come near our truths, are also nibbling here though they handle it another way; for they will have it too, <hi>That all men are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through their own wilful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esse in resisting evident things,</hi> &amp; say <hi>Though Christ as a Prophet sent from God may be easily conceived by hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Reason, yet an infallible Church to govern his flock is easier comprehended and easier demonstrated to a Christi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, than his being sent can be proved to an Infidel</hi> &amp; so forsooth this <hi>infallible Church</hi> by its <hi>definitions,</hi> &amp; <hi>explications</hi> makes the hardest <hi>mysteres</hi> as easie as the plainest</p>
            <p>I here set down this pretty <hi>Doctrine</hi> dress'd after the <hi>Roman fashion,</hi> to show, that if a <hi>Protestant</hi> should not ground damnation on our wilfulnesse in rejecting things within the reach of our capacity, that very <hi>Papis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> themselves will rise up in judgment against him at the last day, to his utter confusion &amp; shame.</p>
            <p>This <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> the eminent <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctor Taylor</hi> himselfe highly esteem'd, &amp; this he so stoutly maintain'd in his book of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Prophecying,</hi> that to this day it remaines unanswer'd. Many enemies I know he created to himselfe by his reconciling <hi>zeale,</hi> &amp; though by their cry he passes at present for a better <hi>practicall</hi> than <hi>controversial Divine,</hi> yet he has (as all men acknowledge) made it evidently appear inconsistent with <hi>Protestant charity</hi> to damne any of our poor <hi>Dissenters</hi> for their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For first, can any godly <hi>Protestant</hi> thinke a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> a limme of Satan for refusing to conforme to <hi>habits</hi> and <hi>ceremonies,</hi> which every body confesses were neither commanded by Christ, nor his Apostles: or shall he be reprobated for railing against stage playes though the drift of the best of them is to abuse the <hi>Brethren?</hi> Nor can the disowning of <hi>Episcopacy</hi> be damnable, unlesse we submit our selves to <hi>Tradition</hi> &amp; <hi>Ecclesiasticall authority</hi> for the <hi>Scripture</hi> has many seeming arguments for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109264:3"/>that opinion. <hi>Predestination,</hi> &amp; the manner of <hi>Christs</hi> descent into Hell are points disputable among all <hi>Christians,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> forbid we should thinke that every error in judgment will deprive us of all happinesse hereafter.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iudependents</hi> or <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> owe their being to the foregoing <hi>Sect,</hi> &amp; if they wildly fancy a barne as good as a Church, or a Graduate, not so learned as a Cobler, with other odde extravagancies (the halfe of which no one man can recount) let us not be more rigorous than the <hi>Pope,</hi> who only lookt upon them that came to <hi>Rome</hi> to convert him as mad; &amp; I think neither <hi>S. Peter,</hi> nor his pretended Successors have lockt Bedlams out of heaven.</p>
            <p>Nor shall I damne <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sts</hi> for matters of Faith, whilst they believe the <hi>Trinity,</hi> &amp; can patch up their other <hi>Doctrines,</hi> so as not really to intend thereby the dishonour of our great <hi>Lord</hi> &amp; <hi>Master.</hi> For (as I said before) <hi>God</hi> forbid every errour in judgment should be a sin to death.</p>
            <p>They fancy many promises in <hi>Scripture, That the Church shall never erre, That it is to be visible in prosperity &amp; adversity as a Iudge in all disputes that occurr,</hi> &amp; laugh at <hi>Protestants</hi> for affirming that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, seeing all <hi>Sects</hi> among us quote Scripture for what they hold, &amp; yet the one is quite opposite to the tenets of the other in things of the highest nature.</p>
            <p>They pre ach up <hi>merits</hi> (they say) to encourage men to worke; but tell us expressly (when we urge them with the foulnesse of the <hi>tenet</hi>) <hi>That neither their own actions, nor the actions of any Saint can be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves sufficient to bring them to heaven, did not God premise to accept them as meritorious, and sufficient by the superaboundant merits of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They honour Saints</hi> (they say) <hi>only because they were faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Christ;</hi> &amp; believe, <hi>That these holy Spirits, must needs know our wants by their rejoycing in heaven at our conversion, &amp; That their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for us are much more powerful with God,</hi> than <hi>tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of our friends here below,</hi> which we all often implore: yet they oblige none to pray to <hi>Saints</hi> except they will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They think by our Saviours saying that some sins</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> those against the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi>) <hi>shall not be forgiven in this world nor in the world to come, that it infers, that other sins may be forgiven in this world, and in the world to come.</hi> And therefore <hi>pray for the dead (that have built upon hay &amp; stubble &amp; other imperfect things)</hi> whom <hi>S. Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> declares (they say) shall be saved <hi>so as by fire.</hi> And they more firmly also believe this <hi>Purgatory</hi> because, the <hi>Maccabees (that fought for the maintenance of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s Law) pray'd for their slain Brethren; which</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:109264:3"/>often urge is recorded by an unquestionable <hi>Historian,</hi> if not be a <hi>Divine Writer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to their <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> they say, <hi>That by believing Christ really there, 'tis him they worship, &amp; not a piece of bread. That the thing is no lesse possible according to humane reason than the Trinity: That the words.</hi> THIS IS MY BODY are as plain, as THERE ARE THREE THAT BEAR RECORD IN HEAVEN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <hi>I hat</hi> it is much for their advantage, that all sects of <hi>Christians</hi> in the world grant the <hi>Real presence,</hi> except a few <hi>Calvinists</hi> as they call them.</p>
            <p>By that text of <hi>Scripture, Confess your sins one to another.</hi> They think their <hi>Confession</hi> enjoyn'd; &amp; that <hi>Christs</hi> commission to his Disciples <hi>to binde &amp; loose</hi> authorizes their Priests <hi>Absolutions</hi> and <hi>Interdictions.</hi> And before many of their Books of <hi>Pilgrimages, Reliques, Pictures.</hi> &amp; the like (to show their worship is relative) they print this piece of <hi>Saint Jerom's</hi> Epistle against <hi>Vigilantius <q>We honour the Reliques of Martyrs, to render adoration to him for the love of whom they were Martyrs, wee honour the servants, that what we do for their service may be refer'd to their Master, who sayes, He that receives you receives me.</q>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>I should never have done, were I to set down all their <hi>opinions,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jesuiticall</hi> glosses, but this I must say for them, that they have much lesse to answer, since they really think themselves in the right, &amp; are so united in their <hi>Fundamentalls,</hi> vvhilst the poor <hi>Protestants</hi> (to the great shame &amp; vveakening of the <hi>common cause</hi>) quarrel irreconcileably about nicetyes, &amp; then divide &amp; subdivide vvithout end.</p>
            <p>For be it therefore from us to damne these <hi>Papists</hi> though <hi>ignorant,</hi> especially seeing, vve must do the like then to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> vvho are not only <hi>Protestants</hi> but the first <hi>Reformers</hi> also: for their Churches are cram'd vvith <hi>Crucifixes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pictures;</hi> and vvhich is more, they as really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Christ</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi> himself; the <hi>maine point</hi> in vvhich he &amp; his brood commit <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as the <hi>Church of England</hi> &amp; the other <hi>reform'd Churches</hi> hold.</p>
            <p>Let not therefore our passion shut up heaven against any to whom our <hi>Saviour</hi> has open'd it; &amp; since <hi>Protestants</hi> themselves do so disagree (as sometimes each man in a family is of a different Church) let us be the more charitable in our censures, according to the healing advice of many a painfull <hi>Divine;</hi> and thus may the <hi>Papists</hi> be baffled vvith their ovvn di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, <hi>viz. That they differ in school poynts only, &amp; not in Fundamentalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I desire not to be misunderstood, for I hold many other Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines extremely advantageous to poor souls, &amp; heartily vvish all men of my opinion, but nothing but time &amp; nevv methods can unite us vvithout the utter ruine of the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109264:4"/>
            <p>Having thus like a good <hi>Protestant</hi> prov'd, That <hi>Indulgence</hi> to <hi>dissenters</hi> though (they should encrease by it, as some vainly fancy) cannot hinder their <hi>salvation</hi> because all that do well may be saved; I will now come to the <hi>civil Government,</hi> &amp; show you that it will be so far from causing <hi>disturbances,</hi> or endangering the <hi>true Religion,</hi> that in ten years there shall not be a <hi>dissenter</hi> left to piss against the wall; &amp; this I hope (if practicable) must satisfy even those, that limite <hi>God's mercy,</hi> especially since they know how firmly sects are already rooted here, &amp; could never be extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated by the severity of our <hi>Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have often laught'd to heare persons of each <hi>Sect</hi> among us pretend that their Religion teaches nothing but <hi>obedience</hi> to Magistra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, whilst all others foment <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Now for my part I would absolutely trust no Religion in the world with the full power of deposing Princes, no more then I would have an <hi>Infidel</hi> trust his wise in bed with me because I am a <hi>Christian</hi> 'tis most certain that the true religion of <hi>Christ,</hi> comands as well an exact <hi>obedience</hi> to our <hi>Rulers,</hi> as that we should not <hi>commit adultery;</hi> but yet whilst men are men, many of the Professors of this truth (what by the force of a partial appetite, &amp; selfe <hi>intereste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) when they have opportunity, often transgresse those two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, though as positively commanded as can be: &amp; therefore some doubt whether all the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> would have been so patient under <hi>Nero, Domitian, Diocletian, &amp;c.</hi> had they had power enough to contend: Nor will I more passe my word that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> should continue <hi>Emperour</hi> &amp; <hi>Mahometon,</hi> were the sword wholly in the hands of his <hi>Christian</hi> subjects, than that all the members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> would have submitted to our present <hi>Monarch,</hi> had he yielded to the <hi>Papists,</hi> who were as buisy (they say) as Bees to convert him.</p>
            <p>All men whatsoever affect to have their Prince of their Religion, because they fancy it most for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> but nothing heightens this <hi>zeale</hi> so much as <hi>persecution;</hi> for whensoever their is difficulty of obtaining our will, the desire of enjoyment encreases; as we see even in women that often risque life, fortune, honour, &amp; all to enjoy a <hi>Gallent,</hi> when as if they afterwards marry (&amp; then there will be no need of comming in by the window) tis a thousand to one but they presently loath each others conversation, &amp; bed, Besides this natural pronenesse to pursue what is hinder'd us (for <hi>passion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> often bear sway even in our spiritual actions) selfe preservation also or the hopes to be quiet puts the braines of <hi>dissenters</hi> upon propagating their Religion; nor is it a small argument to many of the truth of a new <hi>Doctrine,</hi> to see men suffer for it.</p>
            <p>This we have experimentally seen here at home in every party that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109264:4"/>now contends with the <hi>Church;</hi> for what could be more irresistible than <hi>Presbytery</hi> in the beginning of the late war; &amp; how many, men, women, &amp; children, would have willingly ventur'd their lives for the <hi>Cause</hi> whilst kept under? &amp; yet within three yeares or thereabouts after it's establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 'twas kickt downe even by those who had before set it up with such <hi>zeale</hi> &amp; <hi>hazard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phanaticisme</hi> (as all mankinde inlightned with the least spark of reason will acknowledge) has no greater enemy than it sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, nor ever did, nor ever can stand, because it wants all <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lement;</hi> &amp; therefore 'tis we that blow the party into some appearance of <hi>unity,</hi> in hoping, by disturbance to hasten their ruine.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Popery,</hi> let us consider it in <hi>Queen Elizabeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> time, &amp; we shall find in our <hi>Protestant Historians</hi> that for the first en yeares of her reigne no man as a <hi>Papist</hi> sufferd either in his life, or Estate, &amp; yet from a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the <hi>Reform'd</hi> became much more than halfe the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> but after that the Government began to enact <hi>sanguinary</hi> &amp; penal Lawes we find that <hi>Allen, Philopater,</hi> &amp; the rest of their active Writers insisted upon no argument more (to prove the truth of their Religion) than that <hi>Protestants</hi> of all sorts became dayly <hi>Papists,</hi> but not one in 7. years left them, except some scandalous fellow which was a greater advantage than losse to them.</p>
            <p>Let us look in the next place on their <hi>Jesuiticall Seminaries</hi> at <hi>Douay,</hi> &amp; <hi>Saint Omers,</hi> &amp; you shall find them (as knowing men have assur'd me) much emptier now they can carry <hi>popish</hi> Children over with little danger, than in the former dayes, when it was done by great bribes, &amp; they often indited for fugitives also.</p>
            <p>Again if we reflect upon our <hi>late Rebellion,</hi> it was called by many (as I vvell remember) the <hi>Popes harvest,</hi> &amp; <hi>Halcyon dayes;</hi> &amp; yet vve knovv they lost besides others of note, tvvo <hi>Marquesses</hi> at a clap (I meane the heires apparent of <hi>Winchester,</hi> &amp; <hi>Worcester</hi>) the like of vvhich cannot be paralleld in the greatest severities of the <hi>Queen,</hi> nor in the violent storme that universally fell after the <hi>Powder Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, Concerning <hi>Proclamations</hi> &amp; the like, what man ever found the least good by them? If there be any thing got, the Priests are the gainers: for (ever body say's) not one stir's out of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; 'tis likely also by being in a seeming kind of danger, that they are the more caress'd by their <hi>Penitents.</hi> Nay if all things vvere vvell examin'd, vve shall finde that the <hi>Protestants</hi> themselves doe ever pitty them in distresse, &amp; that there are never more <hi>conversions</hi> than in the height of these pudders, vvhich 'tis no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109264:5"/>wonder if they enter into their <hi>Annalls</hi> as <hi>Persecutions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>punishment</hi> then serves only to encrease the number of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> why should we be so much their friends, &amp; do them courtesies to be rayld at for our paines? <hi>Courtesies</hi> I say, because their <hi>Domine</hi> or <hi>Godly Pastor</hi> would otherwise starve, whereas now there's nothing thought too good for him; &amp; the flock then would have also leisure to consider their extravigance, vvhich novv the <hi>pleasure</hi> of being <hi>haress'd</hi> hinders. No <hi>Cavaliers</hi> vvill vvonder at my joyning the vvord <hi>pleasure</hi> to <hi>harassing,</hi> since I dare say there are not any of those great &amp; loyal subjects, though they novv possesse places suitable to their merits, but had formerly more satisfaction in one poor play by stealth at <hi>Hayns's,</hi> in one meeting at <hi>Doctor Gunning's</hi> in danger, or in contriving any halfe Moon-plot over a pint of sack, than ever they enjoyed (as to their own particular) since the absolute esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment of his <hi>Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the nature of fraile man, &amp; if the best &amp; wifest of men cool a little by enjoyment, what must they do that have no other guide but <hi>passion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wish then that our <hi>Sectaries</hi> had <hi>churckes</hi> allowed them, &amp; all the <hi>priviledges of their birth right</hi> as they call it; nor am I yet their Advocate, but the Nation's, as hoping to preserve it's Inhabitants &amp; destroy their foolish blind <hi>Zeale,</hi> which hath been so fatal to us.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Congregations</hi> I would have under penalty pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique &amp; register'd, which has nothing of particularity in it, seeing all the <hi>Churches</hi> in the Kingdome are so. By this meanes his <hi>Majestie</hi> would know their <hi>persons, manners,</hi> &amp; <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which now by their meeting in holes, he is wholly unacquainted with; &amp; if any man then spake i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the least against the Government, he should be made an example with all the severity that could be thought of.</p>
            <p>I have heard say that in <hi>Holland</hi> (where no Religion is unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come) if any Minister in his sermon, or other spiritual function, meddles with <hi>state affaires,</hi> the Magistrates send him next day a pair of shoos to carry him forthwith out of the Prouince; &amp; prefent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he provides for his march, otherwise he is sure to be hang'd unlamented; nor do they ever touch more than the <hi>offender,</hi> which proceed's not so much from <hi>Iustice</hi> or <hi>Compassion</hi> as <hi>Prudence;</hi> it being certain no penalty can so surely tye up an Incendiary's tongue as (when he suffers) not to be pittied by his Party.)</p>
            <p>For to punish the whole <hi>Body</hi> (as the English custome is) for the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109264:5"/>faults of some <hi>members,</hi> makes them all desperate, racking many times their brain to defend an action (the then <hi>common cause</hi>) which otherwise they would have disown'd without difficulty; &amp; besides it is a kind of real martyrdom when a man actually suffers either in his life or estate, for a crime which perchance strictly &amp; truly he abominates.</p>
            <p>No wonder then, that our <hi>Papists</hi> not only reckon themselves <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but are cry'd up &amp; esteemed for such by so many forreign Princes; which must needs draw a scandal upon the Nation, &amp; so do the <hi>Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> a prejudice both at home, &amp; abroad, if these encrease, and gain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute also by their sufferings. I cannot therefore but be highly dissatisfyed with our <hi>common Justice'</hi> which entailes Rebellion on a <hi>Sect,</hi> &amp; insulting too much over the weaknesse of mankind, necessarily (as it were) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines from father to son unprincipled men to all villany &amp; Treason.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore call to mind the <hi>Scotch Presbyterian Rebellion</hi> in 66 last, &amp; see what a ruine it would have been to <hi>England,</hi> had his <hi>Majesty</hi> instead of his own great prudence, &amp; mercifull temper followed their councel, who thought it fit to pursue our <hi>Presbyterians</hi> at home, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotters with those actually in arms. This would have driven all into the utmost despair, especially those that loved the <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Kingdom</hi> best; for then they would have deem'd it impossible to satisfye, &amp; consequently thought ill designs the best of their play; nor would they have look't upon themselves or children otherwise than slaves, since no slavery is equall to that, of being always suspected by the Government. Many that are now faithfull, would then have been not only incens'd, but perchance have turned their <hi>Bibles</hi> over &amp; over to find again arguments to maintain <hi>Rebellion,</hi> for what will not men fancy <hi>God</hi> says, when 'tis absolutely necessary for their ends?</p>
            <p>Were every man that now heartily rejoyces at a Thief's execution at <hi>Tyburne,</hi> to suffer with the Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>factour, we should not only see <hi>theft</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by its present condemners, but reckon'd for a <hi>virtue</hi> also. Some would cry up the life of a man for an inestimable jewel, &amp; to be preferred before all worldly trash. Others would term <hi>propriety,</hi> a <hi>tyrannique,</hi> &amp; <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just usurpation,</hi> with the like metaphysicall fancies; nay the tricks of a Ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call would be then called the effect of a dexterons wit, &amp; the setting upon two or three unarmed Grasiers, the height of all valour &amp; courage.</p>
            <p>There's nothing can ever destroy us in <hi>England</hi> but disagreement, nor shall the Government ever fail of being thought the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by all <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> whilst the folly or knavery of some few is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the whole gang in generall.</p>
            <p>If this way of proceeding were lay'd aside (which now strongly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments them) their <hi>Congregations</hi> would quickly be as well satisfied with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109264:6"/>the condemnation of a guilty <hi>Member,</hi> as we ordinarily are at what passes at the <hi>Ola Bayly,</hi> or at any of our other <hi>Sessions</hi> It may be some might strive to mince the matter of fact (as dayly friends to in all faults committed) but none would then defend a crime to be no crime, which is the thing I solely insist upon, for from thence arise all our disputes &amp; factions.</p>
            <p>'Tis an <hi>error</hi> to thinke there can be a great <hi>Boay</hi> of men inconsistent with Government, since to be lawlesse is as opposite to the nature of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in general, as death it self. Every sober man therefore (let his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be what it will) find's out some distinction or other to prevent confusion &amp; to conform to lawes that tend to Government. The <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> are too discreet &amp; rich to be <hi>anarchical,</hi> &amp; whosoever has, &amp; loves riches, will be alwayes fond of laws that preserve his right to them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Phanariques</hi> are generally harmlesse &amp; well meaning, &amp; though a <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker</hi> will not set out his Tithes, he will bid the <hi>Minister</hi> or <hi>Tithing man</hi> take them; nay if he find losse by their carving, he will at length do it himself with this or the like salvo, that <hi>'Tis the old man &amp; not the new that payes the Hireling that Indaical abomination:</hi> nor do these poor people refuse (it seems) to engage to live peaceably, as their friend <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> tells us in his <hi>Great Case.</hi> Now for the <hi>Paypists,</hi> the greatest &amp; most absolute Princes of the World are not only of their profession, but our own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom also was extremely considerable under their <hi>Government,</hi> &amp; our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lawes &amp; prudent old customes were of their framing; as they well know, &amp; also vaunt in their late <hi>Apology</hi> and <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides though the <hi>Papists</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are still so great Assertors of the <hi>Popes</hi> power in <hi>Spirituals,</hi> that I really believe by what I have read &amp; seen) that there would more dye for him here, than in any two Countreyes in the world, yet we know that in the very depth of <hi>Popery</hi> no body struck more bold &amp; home at all temporal encroachments of the <hi>Romish See,</hi> than the <hi>English;</hi> for they not only made strict prohibitions against the <hi>comming</hi> in of <hi>Legates</hi> without leave, against <hi>publication of Bulls,</hi> &amp; the like; but also enacted those nipping lawes of <hi>Mortmain,</hi> so that no body could voluntarily, &amp; of his own head give one foot of land to the <hi>Church;</hi> Nor at this day do I find, (for truly I have made particular enquiry about it) any Frenchman more willing than our present <hi>Papists</hi> to tye up the <hi>Popes</hi> hands from medling with the <hi>civil Government</hi> of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>If therefore all or any of these <hi>Dissenters</hi> be now heaving at the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 'tis because they are distinguish'd from the rest of the <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; made as uncapable of many things as strangers &amp; aliens; nor do's animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity or a rebellious Spirit always proceed from the Religion men professe but from the frallty of nature, which makes them often partial, &amp; take the dictates of their appetite for truth &amp; reason. Now were no <hi>English Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> (as long as obedient to the lawful <hi>Power</hi>) inconvenienc'd for his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109264:6"/>'tis impossible but <hi>Sectaries</hi> would be as heartily sollicitous for the good of the <hi>Nation,</hi> as any men else whatsoever.</p>
            <p>This most evidently appeares by the <hi>Welsh,</hi> who (whilst we suspected &amp; used them with rigour) were ever unquiet, &amp; our most deadly enemies: but after we had recleved them as friends, &amp; made them partakers of all the <hi>priviledges</hi> of the Kingdome, they not only forgot <hi>our strange usage of their Princes, the losse of their lands &amp; the Egyptian slavery</hi> they were under, but so united themselves with us, that our losses are now theirs, &amp; theirs ours; nor have they since ever stirr'd or made ill use of our favours, but (on the contrary) by them, both they and we are become <hi>one people,</hi> &amp; <hi>one nation</hi> without the least rancor, or grudge; nay so fond have they been of our <hi>Monarchy</hi> (which once they hated above all things) that four parts of five of them were faithfull to his <hi>late Majesty,</hi> whilst such a number of <hi>English</hi> were up against him. If then <hi>gentlenesse</hi> &amp; <hi>interest</hi> could reconcile long feudes, &amp; make men from mortal foes become the greatest friends, why may not we expect by the like method the like successe in these our present distractions?</p>
            <p>There's one <hi>argument</hi> (as 'tis thought) of great weight against this <hi>liberty of Conscience,</hi> viz: <hi>That all Dissenters when they were in power would tolerate noe Religion but their own</hi> (as the <hi>Papists</hi> in times past, &amp; the <hi>Protestant Sectaries</hi> in the late Rebellion) &amp; therefore in <hi>Iustice</hi> they ought now to be served in the same manner. The matter of <hi>fact</hi> is granted &amp; taken out of their sermons I knowe, yet neverthelesse if persecuting <hi>Christians</hi> for <hi>Conscience,</hi> be in it selfe against <hi>charity,</hi> we must not retaliate, &amp; render like for like. But on the other side, if the <hi>lawful Magistrate</hi> may punish <hi>tender Consciences</hi> when he thinks it for the honour of <hi>goa,</hi> &amp; the quiet of the Government, this may perchance a little touch the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> &amp; <hi>Phanatique<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (who were our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers by indirect meanes) but then we can never blame any longer the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> for what they did, because their Government (as to its Juridiction) was as lawful as ours, &amp; their <hi>plea</hi> consequently unanswerable, <hi>viz.</hi> That they really <hi>fancy'd their Religion true, &amp; the Protestant heritical; That they thought it would for ever distract &amp; disquiet the nation to permit new Doctrine;</hi> &amp; in short, <hi>That they proceeded according to Magna Charta, &amp; other Lawes enacted by the legal Authority of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Noe man cna therefore better defend the <hi>Marian dayes</hi> &amp; all <hi>Popish se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity,</hi> than by advising the punishment of <hi>Non conformists,</hi> &amp; practising it as we do; But if we would have the <hi>Church of England's</hi> great beauty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, &amp; be the <hi>true spouse without pot or wrsnkle</hi> we must necessarily refrain from doing those things, which they whom we blame are deem'd guilty of.</p>
            <p>It is pleasant to see now adays how <hi>Prethyterians, Independents &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> (though really no great friends) begin to claw one another; &amp; who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109264:7"/>can blame them for it, or would not think them otherwise fools, since they lye all under the same lash.</p>
            <p>I remember when <hi>Doctor Hewet</hi> was to be executed, our <hi>Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> &amp; <hi>City Divines</hi> joyn'd together (though they hated one aonther suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently) to petition <hi>Cromwel</hi> for him; at which some persons of quality wondring one night at <hi>Dr. Duns, Sir Henry Blunt</hi> answered, that he thought here was nothing extraordinary in that action; for (said he) I have neare my house a <hi>Common</hi> where my piggs &amp; my neighbour's feed, &amp; theere I dayly ee that they eagerly fight &amp; bite one another at the trough, But if a dog happens to fall upon any one, the rest will presently take the part of the oppress'd with all the zeale &amp; fury imaginable.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain both <hi>Greek</hi> &amp; <hi>Trojan</hi> will unite when they finde it their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest to do it &amp; what greater interest can any man have, than the <hi>good</hi> of his <hi>Countery,</hi> if he be capable of participating of all the aduantages that accrue?</p>
            <p>I do not therefore inferr that presently a <hi>Quaker</hi> must be made <hi>Master of the Ceremonies,</hi> or <hi>Revelles,</hi> but that if he can dance, &amp; put of his hat with as good a grace as another, he should not loose the hopes of these places by reason of his Religion; for though thousands will never emerge but be Beggars and Tinkers, should all our <hi>Colliass</hi> be fraught with Gold, yet these very contemptible men would think the <hi>Government</hi> uneasie, and perchance wish it's ruine, were they by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> never to rise to any higher pitch.</p>
            <p>Were we all of one <hi>Opinion,</hi> no man should be more willing to keep out <hi>Sects</hi> than my self, for then 'twould be both seaseable and lawful; but since things are come to this height, 'tis now impossible to do it by <hi>Severit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> for all violent courses will only exasperate more than half our subjects, &amp; cause many to catch at all seditious oppertunities that shall at any time accurre.</p>
            <p>But some men (like <hi>Iustice Over doe</hi>) must be punishing, for otherwise they fancy all <hi>Discipline</hi> lost; &amp; therefore of such I would faine know, since all <hi>Disseaters</hi> cannot in <hi>Prudence</hi> be brought to the ring, which of them would they baite had they power?</p>
            <p>To fall soule on the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> would be madnesse, for who would not deem that action so w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> must needs provoak a <hi>rich,</hi> a <hi>prudent,</hi> &amp; a <hi>numorous Party</hi> to be eternal enemies to the Government, &amp; yet no <hi>Protestant</hi> can call their <hi>errours</hi> in Faith damnable. They once err'd we know, but this may be a means to make their children also faulty; &amp; truly I doubt not but the miseries they at last suffer'd in the <hi>late Rebellion,</hi> (for wealthy men must smart in such disorders) will cause them to be for the future <hi>faithfull En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish men,</hi> unlesse new <hi>exasterations</hi> pervert both their <hi>resolution</hi> &amp; <hi>reason,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tvvere pitty also, methinks, to be alvvayes punishing <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> vvho, rather vvant good <hi>Phisitian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cephaliques,</hi> than the <hi>authority</hi> of a <hi>Constable</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109264:7"/>I am sure (as I said before) it makes them more obstinate, as fancying themselves like the <hi>primitive Christians,</hi> whilst the <hi>Hollanders</hi> grow rich by our losses, affording them that quiet which they find not at home, &amp; thereby become masters of those <hi>manufactures</hi> which formerly we <hi>alone</hi> could brag of.</p>
            <p>Or shall we then vent our fury against <hi>Papists,</hi> &amp; make our selves still ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to our <hi>neighbouring Princes,</hi> who receiving odd accounts from their Agents, think us a weak people and casie to be distracted by vain fears &amp; jealousies? Nor can it certainly be for the good or honour of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to persecute those, who have shewed so much <hi>loyalty,</hi> that no race of men could ever parallel them unless the true <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> &amp; that which makes me yet more their friend, is that at present (though we have often provokt them) they keep no <hi>privato cavalling</hi> with either <hi>France, Spain, Pope, Devil,</hi> or any thing that is ill (for had they done it we should have smelt it out long ago) but on the contrary, they have ever the <hi>King</hi> in their mouths, as if the <hi>Rump</hi> were now on foot, &amp; expresse as much grief at our <hi>publique misfortunes,</hi> as any other <hi>Subjects</hi> in the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I defie all their <hi>Priests</hi> &amp; <hi>Fryert</hi> to alter my principles in Religion yet I do acknowledge their <hi>Church</hi> to be a <hi>Church</hi> as our learned <hi>Prelates</hi> &amp; <hi>Divines</hi> have taught me; nor can I but decrie those that will damn our great <hi>Grand-fathers,</hi> and consequently all before them; for I am sure every body then vvere <hi>Papists</hi> vvith a vengeance, unlesse sometimes tvvo or three foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>Lodards</hi> started up, vvho vvere far liker the <hi>Disciples</hi> of <hi>Fox</hi> &amp; <hi>Naylor,</hi> than <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>true Protestant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Avvay then vvith persecuting <hi>Christians</hi> purely for <hi>Conscience,</hi> vvhich is the only <hi>harvest</hi> for <hi>Knaves,</hi> &amp; of this here at home vve have tvvo most vvofull examples; For neither had the <hi>Heads</hi> of our <hi>long Rebellion</hi> been so povverfully assisted at first, could their <hi>zealous Abetters</hi> have been assured of their Religion; Nor vvas it ever possible for <hi>Cromwel</hi> to have rais'd him self to that pitch he was in, but by laying hold on the <hi>tender Consciences</hi> of men, who despairing of favour from a lawfuller <hi>Government,</hi> became at last <hi>bawds</hi> to his <hi>ambition,</hi> &amp; then shar'd with him in that rich &amp; plentiful booty.</p>
            <p>Away I say, with this <hi>persecution,</hi> the chief cause also of to much <hi>Atkeisme</hi> amongst us; for men who want courage to suffer, by sinning often against their <hi>Consciences,</hi> become hardned in time, &amp; instead of ever really appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Religion impos'd, think every thing at last a meer cheat, &amp; so from harmlesse people (erronious it may be at first in points of small con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment) grow sixt by degrees in all <hi>infiaelity</hi> &amp; <hi>prophanenesse;</hi> nor has any one thing been more destructive to our Government than so many <hi>Oathes,</hi> for most that were truly ill men never scrupled the taking of them, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssenters</hi> that stood on <hi>Principles</hi> have always refus'd them, &amp; often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109264:8"/>smartly suffer'd for it. Thus the <hi>best</hi> fall only within reach of the <hi>lawes,</hi> whilst the most <hi>factious</hi> &amp; <hi>dangerous</hi> against whom these very <hi>lawes</hi> were intended) escape their deserved punishment.</p>
            <p>I professe to the whole world I have no inclination to the <hi>Religion</hi> of our <hi>Sectariet,</hi> but their <hi>persons;</hi> who being so numerous can never be misus'd without an unspeakable inconvenience to us all; &amp; though I have been a <hi>Cavalier</hi> (I thank <hi>God</hi>) ever since the name came up (&amp; to this day dote upon any thing that truly was of that <hi>party</hi>) yet I have laid aside all ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosity against our old enemies, because I am sure it is for the interest now of that <hi>Prince</hi> whose <hi>Rights</hi> we all heretofore so eagerly asserted.</p>
            <p>As Rebels against the <hi>State</hi> must be pardon'd whensoever they are many, even so we must do vvith <hi>Dissenters</hi> in Religion, for though the executing of three or four Traytors may be <hi>Iustice,</hi> yet to hang up many millions, would be termed <hi>oruelty</hi> let the fact be what it will.</p>
            <p>Let there then be a <hi>general Toleration,</hi> for unlesse it be generall we shall never be at rest, but furnish <hi>knaves</hi> still (as I said before) with advantages to cousin poor people, &amp; provoke them (being once deluded) to kick against their <hi>lawfull Magistrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Presbyterians</hi> whine their fill, &amp; tell us of <hi>Soulsaving-sending-home-comforts,</hi> let <hi>Phanatiques</hi> sigh till they be in earnest; &amp; let <hi>Papists</hi> tire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with their <hi>Pater Nosters</hi> &amp; <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> &amp; then I am sure they will all of them soon find the honour &amp; welfare of their <hi>Countrey</hi> to be their only <hi>interest.</hi> Nor is there danger that the bare hopes of recovering the <hi>publick Lands</hi> they once bought in the late <hi>civil War,</hi> vvill make the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiques</hi> fond of alterations; since they very well know, let vvhat changes soever happen (which god in his mercy defend us alvvaies from) the <hi>new Adventurers</hi> will get the prey to themselves, for that must be proportioned to each Actor, according to vvhat he <hi>theu</hi> do's, &amp; not to vvhat he or his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>formerly</hi> did: but though by rebellion they can have no assurance of reenjoying their old silly purchasses, or any temporal gain more than other nevv partizans, yet all of them are sure that <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> vvill be granted them from the first, vvhat faction soever takes up armes against the King vvhich must needs make even quiet <hi>Sectaries</hi> greedy to hear of insurrections &amp; broils. Hovv necessary are the means of preventing such an ill? for <hi>wo</hi> be to that countrey to so great a part of vvhose Inhabitants, <hi>sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> &amp; <hi>disorders</hi> are a certain advantage.</p>
            <p>'Tvvere needlesse to mention the many places vvhere <hi>Toleration</hi> even at present is granted, as vvell in <hi>Popish</hi> as <hi>Protestant</hi> Countries, vvhich shovvs all discourses against its unpracticablenesse chimercial, &amp; the idle vvhimsies of mens brains; nay vve knovv that in <hi>Holland,</hi> &amp; in many provinces of <hi>Germany</hi> (besides several <hi>plantations,</hi> in the <hi>East</hi> &amp; <hi>West Indies,</hi> &amp; a thousand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109264:8"/>other places) <hi>Dissenters</hi> are not only good <hi>Subjects</hi> &amp; make the <hi>publick interest</hi> of the <hi>Countrey</hi> their <hi>own,</hi> but also after their playing the fool a while, they become tyr'd at last by being let alone, &amp; then commonly conform themselves to the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Government under which they happen then to be.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all, for <hi>Toleration</hi> will convert several <hi>Sects</hi> from those abominable <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> as to <hi>Obedience</hi> which now they are thought tainted with; because whilst they secretly meet in by places what may not their Pastours infuse into them, &amp; what will they not easily swallow, being discontented and troubled? On the other side, if their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurches</hi> be <hi>publique</hi> &amp; allowed by <hi>Authority,</hi> we may all then not only truly know what is taught by them, but also their <hi>Congregations</hi> (being enjoyned to give up in writing the <hi>summ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of their <hi>tenets</hi>) will without <hi>peradventure</hi> soon conform to the due <hi>obedience</hi> mentioned; for 'tis certain to all mankind that things posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively against the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> as <hi>Murther, Theft, Adultery, Liberty to kill Kings</hi> when we please, &amp; the like) will never be permitted by any Power in the world, &amp; therefore the <hi>Knaves,</hi> or <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of our <hi>Sectaries</hi> (whose ambition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign is to draw people after them) dare not insist upon such <hi>Doctrines,</hi> as knowing it cannot be so much as conniv'd at by his <hi>Majesty;</hi> &amp; instead of being thought martyrs they are sure to be deserted by their own <hi>Followers,</hi> who will soon discover the cheat, when they find the <hi>King</hi> really <hi>Indulgent</hi> &amp; <hi>good natur'd</hi> &amp; shockt at nothing, but at that which is destructive &amp; hurtfull in it self: for us I said before, There's no <hi>Body</hi> of men truly <hi>anarchicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will cause them then at least to explicate the worst, &amp; most seditious <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines</hi> so, that <hi>Rebellion</hi> must be own'd <hi>unlawfull,</hi> and the <hi>persons</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> esteemed <hi>Sacred,</hi> by which great numbers will be undeluded, and made faithfull, seeing that publickly condemned by their own <hi>Assembly,</hi> which now at best lyes <hi>undetermined,</hi> &amp; therefore may be asserted by the <hi>Preacher</hi> when he pleases. Moreover this enjoyning each <hi>Congregation</hi> to give in a <hi>Confession</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> will certainly reduce all <hi>Sectaries</hi> to their wits; for thus they will be accustomed to stand to some <hi>Principles</hi> or other, whereas now they have nothing <hi>positive,</hi> &amp; consequently can hardly be confuted, the only aim of their <hi>politicall</hi> &amp; <hi>cunning Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be then <hi>true Proustant charity</hi> not to damn <hi>Christians</hi> for <hi>Opinions</hi> whilst they agree in the <hi>maine,</hi> If moreover <hi>Sects</hi> are already so fixt, that they cannot be roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out by force without destroying the Nation, &amp; if Severity blinds them that would otherwise see the truth, and makes them persevere in their errors, entailing also a hatred against the Government on most of their Posterity (which at present weakens &amp; may for the future again undo u) where is the fruit of tormenting men for their <hi>consciences,</hi> unlesse it be to furnish our <hi>Sectaries</hi> (especially <hi>Papists</hi>) with an unanswerable argument for any action committed whilst the power was in their hands.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Liberty</hi> were granted, if guilty men only suffer'd and not their <hi>Parties,</hi> &amp; if <hi>Dissenters</hi> were capable of favour &amp; trust, all people would joyn in the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Government, <hi>Delinquents</hi> might be punish'd to the satisfaction of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109264:9"/>the rest &amp; also the designs of all dangerous Milcreants would be wholly frustrated; &amp; in that only consists the only possibility of new troubles. Nor can <hi>Dissenters</hi> by <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>conscience</hi> have any pretence in the least to <hi>Bishopricks, Deancries,</hi> or our other present <hi>Ecclesiastical preferments,</hi> more than to any mans private lands; because they never contributed to them, &amp; therefore the <hi>King</hi> (had he no other title) must dispose of them, being ever <hi>heir</hi> where there is none, &amp; to how many men of parts &amp; learning, our famous <hi>Monarchs</hi> have still from time to time since the <hi>Reformation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed them, no <hi>English-man</hi> can I am sure be ignorant. What <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectaries</hi> give of their own for the maintenance of their Pastours, in <hi>Goas</hi> name let them have it; &amp; as for the claim of <hi>Papists</hi> to the Premisses we need not fear it, though our Ancestors of that perswasion were the Benefactors; for they that got the <hi>Pope</hi> in <hi>Q Maries</hi> time (for the quiet of the Kingdom) to confirm the <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> that sold <hi>Abbey lands</hi> (which makes our title to them unquestionable upon all accounts whatsoever) will without doubt in consideration of <hi>Indulgence</hi> do again the like, should any man be so scrupulous as to defire their release to that little which is still left the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No benefit can there then be to invent new <hi>Sects,</hi> or to continue them, because <hi>Liberty</hi> to do as they please will quite cool (as I said) the <hi>zeale</hi> of men delighted with novelties, nor shall the persons of many now amongst us be admired who under pretence of suffering for <hi>God,</hi> devour Widdowes &amp; Orphans, &amp; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees become the ruine both of <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How great &amp; strong therefore must the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> grow by this <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> vvhen tvvil be no advantage for Deceivers (that novv dayly rage) to rob her of her children, &amp; vvhat shall hinder the sheep that vvent astray to return, when they find neither pleasure nor profit in their folly? Nor shall we then (to the present wonder of mankind) be always <hi>consulting about Religion,</hi> as our v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry <hi>Grammar</hi> has it; nor will our <hi>Parliaments</hi> be longer troubled with the insolencies of <hi>Papists</hi> &amp; <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiques,</hi> which has been the common artifice to divert sober motions, when they ran counter to the private interest of a few. Having thus stated each Party's <hi>principles</hi> &amp; <hi>case</hi> as full as I could (&amp; really believing <hi>Toleration</hi> will so settle us in our <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> &amp; <hi>temporal</hi> concerns, that in a trice neither of them will have any considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies left) I now defie our <hi>Dissenters</hi> themselves to prevent their own ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, though I have discover'd every thing, &amp; show'd them the very <hi>trap</hi> &amp; <hi>pitfall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that their <hi>Leaders</hi> can (I am sure) do, is (as some have already done) to <hi>kinder</hi> under hand that <hi>Indulgence</hi> which they seem so carnestly to desire; for they are sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible enough (as I mentioned) that they will hereby not only loose the present benefit they make of their <hi>followers</hi> (who in peace will soon be weary of them) but also that all their rebellious designs must be frustrated, as being never able to perswade them to fight the <hi>Battailes</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> or in plain English to <hi>rebell,</hi> that already enjoy what they hope for by the danger: &amp; besides all these true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Pity it self cast's something into the <hi>Ballance,</hi> for if <hi>the righteous man be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to his beast,</hi> much more ought we so to be to poor well-meaning <hi>Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>LONDON <date>1672.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>